<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-06-21T17:09:53+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">tanokhina.github.io</title><subtitle>This is a tale of my design journey</subtitle><author><name>Tetiana Anokhina</name></author><entry><title type="html">Notes from Explore navigation design for iOS - Part 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022-06-16/WWDC-Notes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes from Explore navigation design for iOS - Part 1" /><published>2022-06-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-06-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022-06-16/WWDC-Notes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022-06-16/WWDC-Notes"><![CDATA[<p>Explore navigation design for iOS is WWDC 2022 Session number 10001 by Sarah McClanahan. The session ephasises using familiar navigation patterns. Sarah explains how to use Tab Bar, Navigation, and Modal presentation; best practices; and common pitfalls to avoid.</p>

<p>Overall it’s a very useful session. Navigation topic could not possibly fit in a single WWDC session, but watching it gives clear and concise overview of how to use existing iOS navigation structure, dos and don’ts, and empasizes user centric approach.</p>

<p>Large portion of the session is dedicated to tab bars, explains how to choose candidates for tabs, and challenges common practices, like creating a Home tab, hidding tab bar when navigating through a content, or tab-jumps.</p>

<p>You can view full session here: <a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2022/10001/">Explore navigation design for iOS</a>.</p>

<p>This are my notes, highlighting most important things, that I would love to keep as a quick refresher for myself or anyone designing navigation.</p>

<h2 id="navigation-overview">Navigation Overview</h2>

<p>Great navigation is often unnoticed because people are able to focus on content and experience. Navigation involves teaching people about how things behave, where things belong, and how things work in your app.</p>

<p>The goal of navigaiton is to provide enough of a foundation of familiarity so that people can easily discover your content and interact with your app.</p>

<p>Navigation should not deviate from expectation and match natural understanding of the world.</p>

<h2 id="tab-bars">Tab Bars</h2>

<h3 id="use-tabs-to-reflect-information-hierarchy">Use tabs to reflect information hierarchy</h3>

<p>Tab bars are a global navigation control, categorizing an app into different sections. The tab bar represents top-level content, should be the top of your app’s hierarchy.</p>

<p>UI must translate into clear groups to establish relations between different areas of your app. Each tab must be meaningful and descriptive.</p>

<p>Well designed tab bar can hint functionality without seing content.</p>

<p>Good examples of tabs are:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2022-06-16-WWDC-Notes/music-app.jpeg" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p>Listen Now, Browse, Radio, Lirary, Search - hints that this is content-based app, with audio (Music.app).</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2022-06-16-WWDC-Notes/photos-app.jpeg" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p>Library, For You, Albums, Search - content-rich app with strong personalization (Photos.app).</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2022-06-16-WWDC-Notes/clock-app.jpeg" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p>World Clock, Alarm, Stopwatch, Timer - tabs focused on functionality, self-evident, showing exactly what you can do (Clock.app).</p>

<h3 id="balance-features-throughout-tabs">Balance features throughout tabs</h3>

<p>Oftern the first tab is overloaded with features.</p>

<p>Reasons to add content on one tab:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Available at a glance;</li>
  <li>App evolved over time and lost sight of groupping functionality into sections.</li>
</ul>

<p>Downsides of adding content on one tab:</p>
<ul>
  <li>People need to scroll a lot to find what they looking for;</li>
  <li>It takes effort to mentally parse unrelated, disparate features;</li>
  <li>Features competing for screen space.</li>
</ul>

<p>Create balance by distributing functionality throughout your tabs.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2022-06-16-WWDC-Notes/example-overview.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p><em>The example is an app that lets people discover curated cycling routes in cities and create itineraries. With Overview and Settings tabs.</em></p>

<p>Do not be afraid that people won’t discover the rest (beyond the first tab) of your app. It is much easier to understand an app’s functionality when it’s well organized and clearly communicated.</p>

<p>Improve from all the features crammed into the first tab, to clear and straightforward navigation. From a single overwhelming tab to core functionality balanced between tabs, related but distinctly different content and workflows.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2022-06-16-WWDC-Notes/example-before.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p><em>Before: Overview, Settings</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2022-06-16-WWDC-Notes/example-after.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p><em>After: Places, Iteneraries, and Profile</em></p>

<h3 id="how-to-choose-what-to-put-in-a-tab">How to choose what to put in a tab</h3>

<p>Great apps have focused solutions, aiming to do a few things very well, opposed to solving everything. To achive this - extract in a tab the content that people care about the most.</p>

<p>Another justification for a tab-bar item is amount of navigation and content in a workflow. The most important content most likely will contain a lot of details, additional content, and navigation alone.</p>

<p>Avoid adding anything that is not related to the content of a tab bar item. Look for natural relationships.</p>

<p>Ask yourself:</p>
<ul>
  <li>What is this content;</li>
  <li>How people will use it;</li>
  <li>Where can I dedicate a place for them in my app.</li>
</ul>

<p>Communicate your content and functionality clearly, asses where it belongs in your app, and how people engage with it.</p>

<h3 id="avoid-duplicating-functionality-into-a-single-tab">Avoid duplicating functionality into a single tab</h3>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2022-06-16-WWDC-Notes/example-home.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p>A tab titled Home may seems like attractive catchall to showcase functionality. Or maybe because people aren’t engaging with some feature, and you worried that people don’t know that functionality exists.</p>

<p>Avoid repeating functionality as a way to encourage engagement by increasing visibility.  Likewise, avoid duplicating actions of one content on other’s content tabs.</p>

<p><em>In the example: remove “New Itenerary” action, from the Places list, because Iteneraries is a separate tab.</em></p>

<p>In many scenarios it makes sense to present same content on different tabs. But if it’s your app functionality, actions that people take to achieve things, redundancy creates confusion.</p>

<p>In practice, Home tabs disrupt an app’s functionality. Home becomes the tab where every feature fighting for real estate.</p>

<p>Home tab trying to solve a problem of discoverability creates disassociation between understanding content and how to act on it.</p>

<p>Redundancy of feaures prohibits people from understanding where things belong and why.</p>

<h3 id="keep-tabs-persistent-throughout-your-app">Keep tabs persistent throughout your app</h3>

<p>Home tab, and duplicating features, may cause tab-jump because the action exists in another tab too.</p>

<p>Tab-jump is transporting someone to another tab by tapping on an element withing a content view. This is jarring and disorienting and must be avoided.</p>

<p>Avoid hidding the tab tab throughout your navigation. Persistent access to the tab bar gives someone the ability to toggle between differernt levels of information while maintaining context in each.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2022-06-16-WWDC-Notes/example-places.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2022-06-16-WWDC-Notes/example-itineraries.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p><em>People can can look at a new route in the Places tab, and compare it to an itinerary they’re building, by switching to Itineraries tab.</em></p>

<p>This only works when tabs have defined purpose and represent specific categories of content.</p>

<h3 id="use-clear-and-concise-labels">Use clear and concise labels</h3>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2022-06-16-WWDC-Notes/example-slopes.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p>Good example is 2022 Apple Desing winner, Slopes app, with Record, Resorts, Logbook, Friends, and Account tabs. Labels are representatives of the content. User lands on the middle tab. Tabs are specific and easy to understand. Record a ski day, browse resorts, logbook for your stats, compare stats with friends - they all represent core functionality with a succinct label.</p>

<h2 id="recap">Recap</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Use tabs to reflect information hierarchy;</li>
  <li>Balance features throughout tabs;</li>
  <li>Avoid duplicating functionality into a single tab;</li>
  <li>Keep tabs persistent throughout your app;</li>
  <li>Use clear and concide labels.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Tetiana Anokhina</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore navigation design for iOS is WWDC 2022 Session number 10001 by Sarah McClanahan. The session ephasises using familiar navigation patterns. Sarah explains how to use Tab Bar, Navigation, and Modal presentation; best practices; and common pitfalls to avoid.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Redesigning onboarding platform</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022-02-22/Appical" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Redesigning onboarding platform" /><published>2022-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022-02-22/Appical</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022-02-22/Appical"><![CDATA[<!--more-->
<p><a href="https://www.appical.net">appical.net</a></p>

<h2 id="about-the-project">About the project</h2>

<p>Appical is two-sided B2B2C platform that helps HR managers create onboarding experience for their new hires.</p>

<p>The platform consist of two apps. The editor part is for creating onboarding process. And the app for the new hires provides onboarding experience.</p>

<h2 id="my-role">My role</h2>

<p>I was responsible for the whole design process. From conducting user interviews to gather insights and discover pain points to creating interactive prototypes to test ideas with users.</p>

<p>I closely collaborated with product managements and dev team.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/final_product_web_mobile.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<h2 id="challenge">Challenge</h2>

<p>The app wasn’t easy to use, it had boring look and feel, and many other usability and technical issues. Most of our customers wanted to created an engaging and welcoming experience for new employees. But Appical wasn’t able to satisfy this need. That is why many of our customers didn’t proceed with the product after trial period.</p>

<h2 id="solution">Solution</h2>

<p>We set out to completely overhaul the look and feel of the app. We ran 3 weeks of design sprint based on the design thinking methodology, which includes 5 stages: empathise, define, ideate, prototype and test. We eventually created and shipped a fully functional app where companies can offer the best onboarding experience for their new hires.</p>

<h2 id="process">Process</h2>

<p>I started my process with gathering information.</p>

<p>Together with product manager and another UX designer we interviewed 3 our big customers to find out about their onboarding process. Besides that, we closely collaborated with our sales team to discover the most requested features. As well, we talked to customer onboarding team to hear what struggles the customers have with an existing product.</p>

<h2 id="insights">Insights</h2>

<p>As a result of the research we identified next pain points:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The app doesn’t have a user friendly navigation.</li>
  <li>The main screen is very cluttered.</li>
  <li>Adding company branding is not user-friendly, and missing features like uploading company logo is a big disadvantage.</li>
  <li>Missing mobile experience.</li>
</ul>

<p>With focus on these problems, I started my ideation face.</p>

<h2 id="redesigning-navigation">Redesigning navigation</h2>

<p>I begin with sketching out ideas for improving the navigation of the app.</p>

<p>In the old design the main screen was cluttered, and there wasn’t clear guidance for the users where to start. I’ve decided clean up the main page and leave only important elements.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/early_sketches.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<h2 id="wireframes">Wireframes</h2>

<p>Through the wireframes I was able to design user flows, navigation, and interactions. The wireframes went through various rounds of iteration and I worked closely with dev team to determine technical feasibility.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/iterations_wireframes.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<h2 id="a-focus-on-a-journey">A focus on a journey</h2>

<p>We wanted to create an experience that guide people through their journey without distractions.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="creating-new-brand-settings">Creating new brand settings</h2>

<p>The most requested feature was adding company branding inside the app to create a connection between company and their new hires.</p>

<p>In the old version of a design, user could change a colour of a background, a colour of a text, and add 2 secondary colours.</p>

<p>The problem was that it didn’t give much of a flexibility. And it wasn’t really clear on what elements the 2 secondary colours will be applied. Because of that, the text in some parts of the app became illegible due to colour overlapping.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/theming_designs.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<h2 id="new-settings">New settings</h2>

<p>We come up with the next settings for the theme: the background colour, the button colour, and the title colour. The colour of the text was generated based on the colour of a background. Other elements like icons or lines were connected to the button colour or to the text colour (their colour were generated based on a background colour).</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/pages_designs.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p>I put a lot of effort to check if the new brand settings work well. I created a lot of designs with different colour palettes to see if there wasn’t any colour overlaps.</p>

<p>The new settings gave a much of flexibility to create a true brand of the company inside of the app.</p>

<h2 id="validation">Validation</h2>

<p>On the prototyping stage I conducted a usability testing with users and got my learnings on certain usability issues, so I refined my designs again (and then again after another usability testing).</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/webplayer_prototype.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<h2 id="results">Results</h2>

<p>Our team created a new website with a great navigation structure. We aimed for a clean and modern look. We placed a great emphasis on content, and removed everything that could distract. The new branding rules give our customers more flexibility to create a welcoming experience for their new hires.</p>

<p>As a result we were able to increase customer retention and get a new customers like Van Gogh Museum and PepsiCo.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tetiana Anokhina</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Improving checkout process</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022-02-21/Improving-checkout-process" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Improving checkout process" /><published>2022-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022-02-21/Improving-checkout-process</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022-02-21/Improving-checkout-process"><![CDATA[<h2 id="about-the-project">About the project</h2>

<p>Crowdservice is an auction-based job-search mobile app. It enables users post jobs or place bids to win one.</p>

<h2 id="my-role">My role</h2>

<p>I’ve worked with Crowdservice as a UX/UI designer. I helped improve usability of checkout process and redesigned existing navigation to make it intuitive and easy-to-use.</p>

<p>Besides that, I helped to redesign the look and feel of the app.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/crowdservice_screens.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<h2 id="challenge">Challenge</h2>

<p>The app had a number of usability issues that cause users to switch to competitors.</p>

<p>The key functionality like checkout and bidding process were not user friendly. Based on the research data, people mostly give up on those stages.</p>

<h2 id="process">Process</h2>

<p>I’ve started my process with gathering information about the product goals, its users, their pain points and needs. Stepping into the users shoes and using the product by myself, helped me identify usability issues.</p>

<p>In between, I conducted market analysis in order to understand what other projects like ours offers to their customers.</p>

<p>With all needed insights, I rolled my sleeve and started mapping out user flows and sketching ideas with improvements.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/app_flows.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p>The app has around 7 possible ways to complete a job.
This part was the most challenging during working on the project. I had to identify and note down the possible pain points that people could face during the process.</p>

<h2 id="issues-i-identified">Issues I identified</h2>

<h3 id="bids-and-active-jobs">Bids and active jobs.</h3>

<p>Problem:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Complex informational structure;</li>
  <li>Multiple levels of information;</li>
  <li>Visually hard to differentiate job states.</li>
</ul>

<p>Solution:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Added segmented controls;</li>
  <li>Grouped content;</li>
  <li>Created visual identity of different states.</li>
</ol>

<p><img src="/assets/images/problem_1.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<h3 id="placing-a-bid">Placing a bid.</h3>

<p>Problem:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Information about fee was hidden from a bidder.</li>
</ul>

<p>Solution:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Added details about fees and earning amount.</li>
</ol>

<p><img src="/assets/images/problem_2.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<h3 id="job-info-after-placing-a-bid">Job info after placing a bid.</h3>

<p>Problem:</p>

<ul>
  <li>No clue that the bid has been placed.</li>
</ul>

<p>Solution:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Reminder shows amount of a previously placed bid;</li>
  <li>Added expiry date timer;</li>
  <li>Highlighted day and time of the job;</li>
  <li>Text of the button changes to “Bid again”.</li>
</ol>

<p><img src="/assets/images/problem_3.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<h2 id="validation">Validation</h2>

<p>It was time to validate assumptions and test the redesigned checkout. With the help of the client, I manage to plan a total of 5 online user testing sessions: 3 with people who want to find someone help with their daily choir, and 2 with people who want to perform these kind of jobs. As a reward we offered an Amazon gift card.</p>

<p>It took me around a week and a half to prepare a script and clickable prototype. My client helped organise and schedule calls with our users.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/prototype.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p>The testing helped me spot new insights like:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The info about the bid fee was not clear to people;</li>
  <li>Labels of statuses were confusing;</li>
  <li>The cancelation of a job still was confusing.</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/assets/images/ios_android.png" alt="alt text" /></p>

<h2 id="results">Results</h2>

<p>10% increase in user engagement within 3 weeks of launch.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tetiana Anokhina</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[About the project]]></summary></entry></feed>